Guide to the Confederate States of America Collection 1860-1896 (bulk 1861-1865) MS670.7
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Confederate States of America Collection
1861-1865
MS670.7
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
1.2 Linear feet (3 boxes)
This collection is comprised of records and correspondence relating to the Confederacy and Confederate army. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Arrangement note
This collection has been organized into the following three series:
Series I: Correspondence, records and reports
Series II: Documents relating to the Confederate defeat
Series III: Confederate forms (blank)
Related Materials at the New-York Historical Society
The
Civil War Collection
, MS 670.14 (also an artifical collection) includes documents relating to the Confederacy. Additional materials relating to the Confederacy can be located by searching the library's online
catalog
.
Scope and Contents note
The Confederate States of America Collection is an "artificial" collection of documents that were donated or acquired from a variety of sources but have been organized together by subject matter. The collection consists primarily of government and military records relating to the Confederacy and the Confederate army. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
This material has been arranged into three series. Series I, Correspondence, Records and Reports, includes several folders of official correspondence, primarily of South Carolina Governor Francis W. Pickens and his successor Milledge Bonham. Topics addressed include secession, the formation of the Confederate government and army, and the prosecution of the war. Also included in Series I are reports of battles and field operations, general and special military orders, detail assignments, certificates of disability and discharge, travel passes, quartermaster records, muster rolls, official forms, and legislative bills. Notable documents include a draft of Brigadier General Sibley's Proclamation to the People of New Mexico; a copy of the memorandum setting forth the terms of surrender agreed upon by Generals Taylor and Canby; and a circular issued by the State Collector of Virginia which includes a table showing the average value of slaves in Virginia in 1860. In addition to these official documents, there is one folder of personal correspondence and narratives (including the reminiscences of Leonidas Sebastian Daniel, a telegrapher in Vicksburg), and a list of subscribers to a pamphlet defending slavery on biblical grounds.
Series II, Documents relating to the Confederate defeat, consists primarily of lists of Confederate prisoners paroled at Richmond, Virginia when the Union army took control of the city in April, 1865. Also included is a deposition regarding suspected Confederate guerilla activity and a Confederate soldier's petition for amnesty after the war.
Series III, Confederate forms, consists of blank copies of official forms used by the Confederate government and army, including conscription forms, requests for exemption, and requisition and receipt forms.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Provenance
This is an artificial collection composed of material acquired by the New-York Historical Society at various times.
Bonham, Milledge L., (Milledge Luke), 1813-1890; Confederate States of America. Army. Supplies and stores.; Confederate States of America. Army; Daniel, Leonidas Sebastian, 1837-1922; Daniel, Louise C.; Libby Prison.; Pickens, F.W., (Francis Wilkinson), 1805-1869; Ruggles, Daniel, 1810-1897; Sibley, Henry Hopkins, 1816-1886; Thompson, Meriwether Jeff, 1826-1876; Bills (legislative records); Blank forms.; Bonds (negotiable instruments).; Certificates.; Charleston (S.C.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Correspondence.; Decedents' estates; Desertion, Military -- United States.; Ephemera.; Georgia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Invoices.; Maps.; Military passes.; Muster rolls.; Narratives (documentary genres).; Orders (military records).; Petitions.; Reports.; Requisitions.; Returns (military reports).; Richmond (Va.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; South Carolina--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Telegrams.; Travel documents.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; United States--HIstory--Civil War, 1861-1865--Equipment and supplies; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Hospitals.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons.; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Voters lists.
- Series I: Correspondence, Records and Reports of the Confederacy
  - Correspondence with the Executive Office of South Carolina, 1860 December 20 - 1861 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with the Executive Office of South Carolina, 1862 March 6 - 1865 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Field reports, proclamations, and terms of surrender, 1862 October 2 - 1863 May 23, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Military orders and directives, 1861 April - 1865 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miilitary correspondence, 1861 August 21 - 1863 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Certificates of disability and discharge, requests for exemption, and documents relating to deserters, 1861 May - 1865 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Travel passes and related correspondence, 1861 August - 1865 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Requisitions, invoices and related provisioning documents, 11861 February 19 - 1865 July 10, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Documents relating to civilian property, 1861 October 21 - 1865, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Muster rolls and morning reports, 1862 February - 1865 February, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hospital muster rolls, 1862 - 1864 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oversize muster rolls, undated (Box OS Medium, Folder Y-Confederate States of America)
  - Documents relating to medical and postal services, 1861 - 1864, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Documents relating to taxation and banking, 1861 January 25 - 1865 January 14, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Poll books, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lists of citizens swearing allegiance to Confederate States (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - List of subscribers to pamphlet defending on Biblical grounds the institution of slavery, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personal correspondence, narratives and ephemera, 1861 - 1863, 1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Documents relating to the Confederate defeat
  - Reports and lists of confederate prisoners paroled at Richmond, Virginia, 1865 April (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - List of rebel generals, circa 1865 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Deposition regarding suspected guerilla, 1864 April 4 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Petition for amnesty, 1865 June 17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - List of supplies shipped by U.S. Sanitary Commission for Wilmington, North Carolina, 1865 April 7
- Series III: Confederate Forms (Blank)
  - Forms issued by the Conscription Office, [1861-1865] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Forms relating to exemptions and detail assignments, [1861-1865] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Payroll and muster roll forms, [1861-1865] (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Requisition and receipt forms, [1861-1865] (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Forms issued by the Confederate States of America, [1861-1865] (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Tax forms, [1861-1865] (Box 3, Folder 5)